How exactly do I chunk my data? That's
the first question that comes to mind
when you're building a rack system.
Unfortunately, irrespective of how you
go about it, you're going to run into
issues. You're going to lose either
global or local context. That's why
today we're going to be talking about
contextualized chunk embeddings. Now,
before understanding this, let's look at
a standard rack system. So you have your
document, you divide it into smaller
chunks and normally feed those through a
dense embedding model. Sometimes people
also add full text search and then they
do retrieval on top of that. The problem
is that every chunk that you create
lives in isolation and it doesn't have
any context of its surrounding chunks or
the global document. So there are a
number of different approaches in order
to add context.
One of the most famous one is
contextualized
retrieval prep-processing.
This is an approach proposed by
Enthropic late last year. And the idea
is very simple. You take a chunk, you
feed that chunk along with the whole
document or surrounding chunks to an LLM
and you ask the LLM to create context
around it and then you add that context
to the chunk. The rest of the embedding
process and full text search index is
exactly the same and at retrie time you
just retrieve those contextualized
chunks. Now the problem is for every
chunk you're going to be sending the
chunk plus the document or the
surrounding context to an LLM. So for
larger documents this is going to be
extremely expensive because of the LLM
calls that you're going to be making. So
it's not really feasible. Now another
approach is to do the same thing at
embedding level because embeddings are
usually a lot cheaper. One such approach
is late chunking. The idea is that you
use an embedding model that has long
context. So now we have embedding models
up to 8,000 or even in some cases 32,000
tokens. So you take your whole long
document, you feed it to an embedding
model. The embedding model is going to
generate token level embedding which is
different than a document level
embedding in dense embedding models. But
then you combine those tokens together
to create text chunks and also do a
pooling operation on the token level
embeddings that will give you chunk
level embeddings. Now this approach in
theory can preserve both the local and
global context because the embedding
actually happen at the document level
and since the chunking happens at the
end of the process that's why they named
it late chunking. Okay. So where does
this contextualized chunking comes into
play? Now we're going to look at that
but first let's understand how exactly
the similarity computation works and
what are the drawbacks of different
approaches. So the first one is no
interaction. This happens in most of the
cases if you're doing a dense embedding
based retrieval. In this case you take a
document or a chunk you compute
embeddings independently. You take user
query, compute embeddings and then
whatever the embedding vectors are, you
just compute some sort of similarity
matrix. Usually people compute cosine
similarity. The embedding model hasn't
seen the document and the query
together. So essentially you are looking
at absolutely no interaction and just
trying to find out the similarity based
on the final vector that you get.
Normally this results in bad retrieval.
Now another approach is to do full
interaction. In this case what you do is
you have your chunks and your query fed
into the same model simultaneously
and you say how close this query is to
this document. This is full interaction
which is usually a lot more accurate and
it's a basis of something called cross
encoder. However, this is very comput
inensive and people usually don't do
this on the corpus level. That's why
it's usually used as a secondary step in
a reranker which is a lot more accurate
and is going to give you much more finer
grain results compared to a buy encoder
that you use for the initial retrieval.
Now there is something in between. This
is called latent interaction. The idea
here is that when you compute embeddings
for the document and for the query
independently, rather than getting a
fixed size vector that you usually get
as a result of uh a dense embedding
vector, you compute embeddings at token
level very similar to what I was showing
you in the case of late chunking and
then you compute similarity at the token
level rather than a whole vector level.
Usually people use BERT models for the
initial token level embeddings and then
some sort of similarity metrics at
retrieval time. Colbert is a perfect
example of this. Now this means that
depending on how many tokens are in your
document plus your query, you are going
to get a multi vector representation
instead of a single vector
representation that you get as a result
of a dense model. And in practice, this
usually results in much better retrieval
because you have much more fine grained
embedding models now. But this also
means you're going to need a lot more
storage plus a lot more compute in order
to compute these multiv vector
representations. Okay. So I hope this
gives you a very good idea of different
mechanisms that you can use for
retrieval. This brings us back to
contextualized chunk embeddings. I'm
going to show you a code implementation
that you can run on your own data. But
let's try to understand what exactly
this is. Now in contextualized chunk
embeddings, you take your whole
document. You compute chunks based on
whatever chunking strategy that you want
to use and in the next step you pass
this through a contextualized chunk
embedding model. In this case, the
embedding model is looking at every
chunk along with the original document
from where these chunks are coming from
and it's going to be adding a lot of
global and local context through each
chunk embedding. So here is how it looks
like at query time. You have your user
query. You do a chunk level retrieval.
So you get a chunk but with every chunk
you have the associated contextual
information both on local level as well
as on global level. So you can actually
look at which document this chunk is
coming from along with what are the most
related chunks in that specific
document. Now how is this different from
late interaction or late chunking? In
late chunking, we compute embeddings on
document level and then we create
vectors based on chunk levels. In this
case, we initially divide each document
into chunks and then computings while
preserving the global information. A
quick word from our sponsor today,
emergent. It's a new web coding platform
that turns plain English text prompts
into working full stack web apps. Type
what you want and emergent generates the
front end and back end together. If you
need Google signin, Google
authentication is just oneclick ad. If
you want AI features and don't want to
worry about the API keys, Immersion has
its own internal API keys. Here is a
quick YouTube style clone and a textto
image app from a single prompt.
Immersion pulls all the relevant API
endpoints, builds the app, and even run
integration tests with the AI coding
agent so you can ship with confidence.
So if you have an idea, emergent makes
it fast to go from prompt to working web
apps. Check out emergent link is going
to be in the video description. Now back
to the video. Okay, so here's how the
comparison looks like. Now keep in mind
this is based on their marketing
material. So take it with a grain of
salt. So they're comparing it with
something like dense embeddings from
OpenAI or any other embeddings which
have no context preservation. Then you
have metadata augmentation. You add
summaries or contextual retrieval which
have partial contextual information. Now
in case of the contextualized chunk
embeddings, you're not using an LLM.
You're using an embedding model which is
usually a lot cheaper. But because of
the nature of how this uh embedding
model is trained, you are going to
preserve a lot more context. And usually
uh since you get a fixed-sized embedding
model at the output, the complexity of
integration is going to be very similar
to just replacing it with a a dense
embedding model, right? And according to
them, this gets you the highest
retrieval accuracy. We're going to look
at a code example later in the video,
but I'm going to show you just some
quick benchmarks. So, they did some
benchmarks on different types of data
sets. Now, Voyage
is a very good company. I think now it's
part of MongoDB, but they have been
training some very interesting embedding
models. It's not open source. you have
to pay similar to OpenAI but their
embedding models are being used by
companies like Harway and some code
specific models as well. So you can see
that they have been benchmarking the
embedding models on different niches and
seems to have state-of-the-art accuracy.
This is on chunk level. Here is the same
performance on document level. Seems
like it's outperforming all the other
embedding models on these data sets.
Okay. But a very interesting observation
when I was looking at some of their
data. So if you look at increasing chunk
size in terms of number of tokens, a
normal dense embedding models will
usually have better retrieval accuracy.
So they have voyage 3 large. This is
their dense embedding model. You can see
the retrieval accuracy increases as you
increase the chunk size. But for the
voyage context 3 model, interestingly
the retrieval accuracy actually drops as
you increase the number of tokens in the
chunk. So in this case you want to keep
the chunks to smaller size. Now the only
problem is going to be if you keep the
chunks too small again you're going to
run into storage issues. So you'll have
to find a balance. But the good thing is
that it also supports quantization of
these embedding models. Right? So here
are the accuracies or quality based on
different quantization level. You can
use binary quantization which is going
to save you a lot of money. 4 bit and
then that's 16 bit. Right? So if you
look at the quantization even if you use
binary quantization at 2048 vector size
it gives you very close retrieval
accuracy to using the full size. I would
say there is probably around 2 or 3%
drop right but this uses dynamic size.
So there are multiple different
embedding size that you can use. Before
showing you a code example let me walk
you through the pricing. So this is
around 18 cents per million token. The
first 200 million tokens are free. As a
comparison, here is the Gemini embedding
001. This is their latest multimodel
embedding which is about 15 cents per
million token. Okay, so let me walk you
through a quick example and then I'll
show you a code that you can run on your
own machine. So let's say here are eight
different chunks. In this case, we're
using chunk level or sentence level
chunking, right? So, you can see that
these talks about different quarterly
earnings for different companies. Now,
let's say our prompt is what was the
revenue growth for Leafy Inc. in Q2
2024. So, if you look here, the first
chunk is this is the SEC filing on Leafy
Inc. Q2 2024. The second chunk says the
company's revenue increased by 15%
compared to the previous quarters.
Right? Now in the same document you can
see a very similar situation. The first
chunk talks about a company. The second
chunk talks about a revenue increase or
decrease for the same year. But the
second chunk does not have the company
information neither which quarter or
year it's talking about. So if you were
to do re-ranking based on y3 large since
the question is talking about leafy ink
the normal dense embedding model
basically picks this as the first chunk
now it does have information about Q2
2024 but it doesn't have any information
about the actual revenue of the company
the second chunk which is actually
ranked eighth in this case does not
specifically mention the company by name
when you use the context 3 embeddings
since it preserve both the global and
local context so it knows which company
this specific chunk is talking about.
Now this is an example from their
documentation. So I'm going to walk you
through a real example of my own
testing. So let's have a look at the
notebook now. Okay. So here's the
documentation where they talk about
contextualized chunk embeddings. Okay,
but you need to sign up and initially
also connect your credit card in order
to use the embedding models. But the
first 200
million tokens are free and I think you
need to add only $5 to your account.
Okay, so here's how the structure of
your documents is going to look like.
you are going to divide your document
into smaller chunks and then just pass
on a list of lists with the chunk ids.
Okay, so this Google collab notebook is
going to be available. The first thing I
did here was create a custom class for
chunking my documents. I am doing
sentence level chunking. Depending on
the structure of your document, do it
either on paragraph level or maybe
section by section. So then we take
every document that is going to be
coming in. We create chunks which is
basically isolating each sentence and
then we are going to create this object
where I'm keeping track of the document
title and essentially some other
metadata including what was the location
of every chunk or every sentence in the
document. So at the end of the day when
we do the chunking we create a list of
lists that is going to contain all the
chunks. I am using 1024 probably an
overkill in this case since the document
size is going to be much lower. So play
around with this parameter but we just
provide our input documents. Now in the
other case I'm also computing the
standard embeddings and I just wanted
you to see what type of results I will
get when I use the standard dense
embedding versus the contextualized
embeddings and at runtime we do search
on both of those. Now let me show you
the actual documents that are going into
the into the embedding model. So here is
a document about AWS S3 technical
documentation. It specifically talks
about AWS. What are the storage classes?
What type of encryption we use? What are
the different access controls? Then
here's another document that I created.
It talks about similar setup for Azure.
And then there is a compliance
requirement document for FinTech, right?
So, three different documents. Two of
these have very similar information. And
here are some of my queries. What
encryption does AWS use for SSE KMS? In
this case, the actual information
appears without AWS, right? So, what I
did was I ran the same I think five six
queries through both of the embedding
models and just did retrieval on top of
both of those. Okay. So, I'm not going
to bore you a lot with the internal
mechanism, but for each one of them, I
am retrieving the top three documents.
For example, what encryption does AWS
use for SSE KMS? So you can see that
both of them actually identified the
correct chunk in this case. Now the
second chunk is also coming from AWS.
Yeah, I think both of these models does
a pretty good job at retrieving the
relevant chunk at the top of the
retrieve documents. Same is the case for
the other part as well. it does return
the correct information in terms of the
retrieve document. Now the third one is
what are the storage costs for archived
tier. So in this case the contextualized
chunk embedding actually retrieved the
most relevant chunk at the top and the
standard embedding model I think doesn't
even retrieve that specific chunk at
all. Now here's another one. What is the
data retention policy for audit logs?
Now the first two chunks are relevant.
The second chunks are also relevant. In
case of the contextualized chunk
embedding, it actually returned a chunk
that was or a sentence that is part of
the same paragraph. But the standard
embedding model actually retrieved the
third chunk which is not part of the
data retention policy. For example, if
you look here, this talks about the
platform must maintain, delete detailed
records of all data processing
activities including purpose,
categories, retention, etc. But if you
look at that specific section, it only
talks about those three sentences that
were returned by the contextualized
chunk embeddings. And we see very
similar issues with the customer
identification program policies as well.
In this case, even the second and third
chunk that is coming from the standard
chunk embeddings is actually irrelevant.
So here's the actual part which talks
about customer identification program.
So this was a quick overview of
contextualized chunk embeddings. Do
check it out. I think it's a good tool
to have in your tool set. But keep in
mind whenever you're designing rack
systems, the choices really depends on
how your data looks like and what
exactly the retrieval setup is supposed
to look like. So there's no one fit all
solution when it comes to the
traditional retrieval augmented
generation systems. But it's always good
to know these new techniques because
they can come in very handy. Anyways, do
let me know what you think, how your
experience with this new method is and
also put your questions in the comment
section below. I'm going to try my best
to respond to them. Anyways, I hope you
found this video useful. Thanks for
watching and as always, see you in the
next one.